Arsen Arakelian

Backend Software Engineer

Current location: Berlin, Germany Telegram Gmail LinkedIn GitHub

ABOUT ME

As a **Backend Engineer with 4+ years of experience in Software Engineering.** I have experience working primarily with **Node.js and Cloud Solutions with AWS**. Worked in various sectors like **healthcare**, **education**, **e-commerce**, **and infrastructure automation (IDP)**, so I can adapt to different domains.

SKILLS

Languages: JavaScript, TypeScript

Technologies: Node.js (Express.js, Nest.js) GraphQL (Apollo), RabbitMQ, Redis, Stripe

Databases: PostgreSQL, TypeORM, Knex.js, MongoDB, Mongoose

DevOps: Linux, Docker, Kubernetes, ArgoCD, GitHub, GitLab, AWS (EC2, S3, Lambda,

AWS SAM, EKS), Terraform, Ansible

EXPERIENCE

Backend Engineer, Kepler Technologies | Contractor

01.2023 - Present

Project description: <u>meMR</u> Health, is a fully automated AI platform for efficient record retrieval and data transformation.

Responsibilities:

- Developed a doctor-specific admin panel to replace the Zoho dashboard.
- Migrated from Firebase to AWS Cognito for streamlined services.
- Boosted development and testing efficiency through CI process implementation.
- Created and optimized indexes for PostgreSQL
- Optimized dynamic pdf file generation from 80 sec to 15 sec.

Tech Stack: TypeScript, Node.js, PostgreSQL, Docker, GitLab, AWS (Cognito, EC2, IAM, OpenSearch)

Software Engineer, EPAM Systems | Full Time

12.2021 – 01.2023

Project description: Internal Developer Platform for automating infrastructure processes for Travelers.

Responsibilities:

- Worked on an Internal Developer Platform for automating infrastructure processes and environment setup which reduced onboarding time by 2.6x!
- Configured CI/CD processes, including ESLint, Prettier, GitHub Webhooks/Actions, and ArgoCD for Kubernetes.
- Used Xstate.js for dynamic task management within a state machine.
- As a Key developer, I managed interviews and onboarding for new team members and engineers.

Tech Stack: TypeScript, Node.js, MongoDB, Jest, XState.js, Docker, Kubernetes, ArgoCD,

SonarQube, AWS (SAM, Lambda, API Gateway, IAM), Hashicorp (Vault, Terraform)

Non-project activities: Mentored 3 mentees in the Global Node.js Mentorship Program. Conducted code reviews to ensure quality and industry standards. Organized Q&A sessions and paired programming for effective learning.

JavaScript Engineer, MobiDev | Full Time

05.2021 - 12.2021

Project description: Created **new features and fixed bugs** for **STEERUS** which is specified in **education of soft skills.**

Responsibilities:

- Developed GraphQL schemas and services for user requests.
- Implemented features for uploading images and videos to AWS S3 for tutors.
- Developed real-time streaming lessons functionality using Mux.
- Implemented the **whole checkout and billing feature with Stripe** for ordering the courses.
- Improved database efficiency with raw SQL queries by using knex.js.

Tech Stack: TypeScript, Node.js, GraphQL, AWS (RDS, EC2), PostgreSQL, SendGrid, Stripe, Mux, Ngrok, Docker

Project description: <u>AVELYN</u> is an online platform that connects wine producers and enthusiasts.

Responsibilities:

- Developed the whole search functionality for users to find wines by name or brand back/front sides.
- Implemented a filtering and sorting functionality for wines based on region, grape, and style.
- Implemented the whole checkout and billing feature with Stripe for ordering wines.

Tech Stack: TypeScript, Node.js, Nest.js, React, Redux, AWS (RDS, EC2), PostgreSQL, Docker, Stripe

Node.js Engineer, Chi Software | Full time

06.2020 - 05.2021

Project description: Upgraded <u>Chewy's</u> system from a Python/Django monolith to a more efficient Node.js and TypeScript microservices architecture.

Responsibilities:

- Implemented 2 services for dynamic price calculation and logistic processes from 8 microservices.
- Managed 5 service chains flow of queues for efficient data flow.
- Optimized database queries for improving ORM performance.

Tech Stack: TypeScript, Node.js, AWS (RDS, EC2, SNS, SQS), PostgreSQL, RabbitMQ, Docker

EDUCATION

Kharkiv National University of Economics (KNUE)

09.2014 - 12.2019